Okay, so imagine it's
1 .9 million years
ago and you hear
a deep growl in
the bush. What do
you do? A child
might go over to
it, super curious, but
as an adult you
know from experience that
a deep growl in
the bush is probably
a bad thing. So
you'd be scared and
you'd run or you'd
hide or you'd just
like freeze. The reason
I'm telling you this
is because humans are
wired to pay attention
to things that make
us feel something like
fear, hope, surprise, surprise,
excitement, curiosity, and those
feelings then drive our
actions so that we
don't get eaten by
a bear. But not
only that, when something
moves us emotionally our
brain's hippocampus which stores
memories fires up too.
So in this video
I am going to
show you how to
structure your content to
harness the way our
brains are wired that's
been working to educate
people for millions of
years. You're going to
learn how to structure
a video to get
people's attention, how to
make them feel something,
how to help them
remember what you said,
and most importantly you're
going to make content
that moves them to
act which is absolutely
critical for your channel
and your business's success.
Because if they act,
take an action, and
it works out for
free they come back
and give you money.
Which kind of rhymes.
Okay so let's start
with the basic formula
for achieving this result
and as you remember
it's made up of
two halves emotion and
logic. And we do
this like so. Okay
so tell me what
goes through your head
when you see this
image. It's not the
image of a person.
It's the image of
a person. It's the
image of a person.
It's the image of
a person. It's the
image of a person.
It's the image of
a person. It's the
image of a person.
It's the image of
a person. The poor
ickle puppy whoppy is
going to get hit
by a train is
it? You are disgusting.
That's just two photos
slammed together. The puppy's
in Switzerland, the train's
in Japan. It's not
in danger at all
you sicko. Anyway that's
how you create an
emotional reaction by creating
a visual image in
your viewer's mind that
helps them put the
information together for themselves
in a way that
they can clearly picture
up here. When you
do this information feels
new, easy, and inspiring.
And this is called
showing not telling. And
it's very powerful. Anyway
then after that you
follow up with the
logic brick because once
the emotion is there
the viewer becomes more
open to learning deeper
information. So inside the
logic brick we have
step -by -step points,
lessons, or a mistake.
Basically just more raw
instructions. And this is
when we tell. Now
this emotion logic structure
is not mumbo jumbo
that I have made
up. It's known as
dual process theory and
it's used in sales
and marketing all of
the time because people
make decisions based on
two systems. System one
is basically emotional reaction
and system two is
logic where people are
more slow and deliberate
about their thoughts. So
if you want to
create change in your
viewers and trust me
you do, all we
need to do is
emotion logic. But how
many times do you
use emotional logic in
a script? Well most
videos are often made
up of several points.
It could be three,
five, ten, eleven, twelve,
thirteen, fourteen, fifteen, sixteen,
seventeen, eighteen, twenty. It
doesn't really matter. But
let's just say for
the purpose of this
example the video wants
to make three points
or three lessons. And
if that was the
case this is what
a video's structure might
look like. Intro, point
one, point two, point
three, end screen. And
then you can see
inside every point is
emotion then logic. Just
repeated. So that's one
way of doing it.
But let's say your
video has 10 instructional
steps like editing a
video or baking a
cake. In that case
the structure might be
more simple. So let's
say you're making a
cake. You're making a
cake. Like this where
you have an intro
then one emotion driven
setup and then after
that you just list
the 10 steps clearly
in the logic brick
and then you finish
on the end screen.
So for something like
a step -by -step
tutorial you don't have
to put in emotion
into every single step
because that could potentially
slow down the follow
-along instructions people are
going with and could
confuse the viewer. Now
you're probably thinking oh
how do I know
what to do? When
should I use it?
I'm panicking. Well don't
worry because I've made
you a little decision
matrix to help you
work out how much
emotion logic to put
into a video. So
it works like this.
If your video is
persuasive, trying to persuade
someone of something that's
important like I'm doing
right now, or it's
story driven or it's
insight based, or you're
teaching big ideas or
mindset shifts or you're
trying to challenge beliefs,
you need the viewer
to feel something first
so that their behaviour
will change. And what
that can mean is
each point you make
can benefit from emotion
then logic. So you
would in that case
use the emotion logic
over and over again.
But if your video
is instructional or tutorial
based like 10 editing
steps to get faster,
you're teaching a process
so you just need
to hook attention once
at the start and
then deliver on those
steps quickly so that
we match and exceed
our viewers expectations. So
in that case you
might just use the
emotion brick at the
start of the video
to set up the
big problem and then
deliver into the steps
that will solve them.
Again this is the
sort of thing that
really is going to
become a problem. So
if you're teaching a
video and you're trying
to get it to
become second nature with
more practice, but just
keep in mind this
is not a set
in stone rule. Please
do not fall into
the overwhelm trap where
you constantly think oh
if I miss an
emotion part of the
script the video is
going to fail and
YouTube's magic algorithm isn't
going to punish me
and everything's going to
be over. My retention
graph is going to
explode into a million
pieces.
Sorry. Nobody dies if
you tweak this a
little. The most important
thing is we make
videos that feel new,
easy and inspiring and
that you over time
start to realise that
oh this is information
I'm trying to explain
is complex or I
need it to challenge
a belief or I
need it to change
their mindset so maybe
I need more emotion
bricks in to help
it sink in more.
But how do you
get to that level?
Well by using our
fail as fast as
you can system. I've
been practicing it over
years. This really is
an insanely powerful skill
but it doesn't just
get easy because you
watched a video. You
have to stick to
this for the long
term. The thing is
how do you actually
create emotion and what's
the best way to
use logic? Well there's
lots of different tools
so in the next
series of videos I'm
going to show you
which ones to focus
on. So if you're
interested in learning how
to focus on a
master and then later
on I've made templates
for every type of
video format that you
can try showing you
the best use of
emotion and logic in
it. But just know
this little simple brick
system is all a
great video really is.